If you pray
哪怕你祈祷
until you can pray no more.
直至无法再继续
If you sigh to the breaking of your loins.
哪怕你呜咽叹息直至腰酸背痛
And every sigh a tear,
每一声叹息都化作泪水
and every tear a drop of blood.
而每一滴泪水则化作鲜血
Yet will you have lost all by the commission of that one sin
你也会一无所获 只要你犯下这项罪
of disobedience!
悖逆之罪
When your hearts swelled with false pride
当你满心虚妄的骄傲
and God's command was disobeyed,
违背主的吩咐
then came all the other sins.
其他的罪孽也便随之袭来
Of murder and adultery
谋杀 通奸
and fornication!
乱伦
And when God's voice in England was stopped,
当上帝的声音不再传抵英格兰
when our great nation descended into darkness,
当我们伟大的国家陷入黑暗
Then came female licentiousness and whoredom all around us.
就只有娼妇在我们身边纵淫荡欲
For what woman now knows her place in the world?
因为怎样的女人才会在这世上找到立足之地?
Who are you?
你是谁?
I am as I am. Pull him down.
我就是我 把他拖下来
Leave him!
放开他
There is no Hell.
这世上没有地狱
She blasphemes!
她亵渎神灵
Except when your children cry,
除了你亲生骨肉的哭泣
No women preachers!
不许女人传教
with empty bellies.
因他们食不果腹
There is no heaven, except where you find the universal love
这世上没有天堂 除非你发现博爱
that is there in your hearts.
驻于你心
Be not afraid of these phantoms
但不要畏惧这些幻象
that are nothing but the nightmares
那不过是些梦魇
of his foolish imaginings and all like him
出自他这种人们愚昧的臆想
that would keep you in your accustomed places.
一心让你们裹足不前
Arrest her! Bring her out!
逮捕她 把她带走
Away with her!
离她远点
Take her away.
把她带走
The Palace of Whitehall London
伦敦白厅
Bring her.
把她带来
What shall I call you now, madam?
我现在该怎么称呼您 夫人?
Your prisoner, my Lord?
您的犯人 大人?
No.
不
Mistress Sexby, then.
那就塞斯比夫人
Your friends, the Ranters,
您的朋友 那些喧嚣派
the High Attainers...
进取派...
They find holiness in tobacco and alcohol and fornication.
他们在烟草 酒精 淫乐中寻找我主
God in an ivy leaf,
上帝在常春藤叶中
God in yourselves.
上帝在你心中
And the Bible is wastepaper.
圣经不过是一卷废纸
Who tells you this?
谁跟你说的?
I fear you mean to crush us as you did the Levellers.
恐怕您是要扫清我们吧 像对平等派那样
Bluntly, madam,
直说吧 夫人
in a world without Hell, how will I uphold the law?
这世界没有地狱的话 我又如何维系法律?
Was this the freedom you fought so bravely for,
这便是您浴血奋战争取的自由吗
my Lord General?
将军大人?
All that we fought for is in the balance.
我们是在为和谐世界而战
There is anarchy abroad and the Parliament want an iron hand.
无政府主义横行 议会想用铁腕掌控
The Parliament wants money and land.
议会想要金钱和土地
It took my land, gave it to Master Joliffe to enjoy for life.
他们夺走我的土地 送给若利夫先生终生享用
Master Joliffe, who called me a whore.
若利夫先生 管我叫荡妇的人
There are some that would like the clocks to be turned back.
对 有些人希望时光倒流
But I will not let them, for all their bleating in Parliament.
但我不会让他们如愿 不管他们在议会如何胡扯
Then leave my friends free to speak the love in their hearts.
那就让我的朋友自由说出心中的爱
You are certain of their hearts?
你了解他们心中所想?
We seek an honest way to live on earth now,
我们在寻找一条坦然的存活之道
not in terror of what's to come.
而不是畏惧面前的一切
Yet you blaspheme, madam.
可您亵渎神灵 夫人
What, will you burn me?
那又怎样 你会烧死我?
Put a branding iron on me?
还是在我身上打上烙印?
Hang me?
绞死我?
Have a care, Angelica.
小心点 安吉丽卡
There is a world of difference
自由与纵欲
between freedom and licentiousness.
是截然不同的两个世界
And think of me as your friend.
把我当作你的朋友
Visit me. My old friends, they veer away from me now.
常来看我 我的老朋友都离我而去了
My lady.
夫人
This is the body of Christ.
这是上帝之躯
This is the blood of Christ!
这是上帝之血
I must confess to you.
我要向您忏悔
My heart is not true.
我心有不诚
It betrays me every hour that I'm with you.
与你相处的分分秒秒 它都在背叛着我
I'm lured on a desire
我被欲望诱惑
that a world tells me what I conceive with you is sin.
这世界告诉我眷恋于您是罪过
Is love a sin, madam?
爱是罪过吗 夫人?
Tell me...
告诉我...
it is not a sin.
那不是罪过
I am married, Christian.
我已为人妻 克里斯廷
In outward form only.
那只是形式上的
Yet I will not dishonour him.
即便如此我也不会令他受辱
Why did you resign your commission?
你为什么要辞职?
Still no better man for a fight in these islands.
尽管如此 国中也没有更出色的战士了
I am finished with fighting.
我厌倦了争战
Well then, I have other work for you.
那好 我给你其他工作
Honest John has met with the Cavaliers.
正直的约翰在与王党勾结
They've talked about bringing in the King's son from France.
他们企图把国王的儿子从法国带来
I know this to be true.
我确信这是真的
How "know it"?
你怎么知道的?
We have agents among the malcontents.
我们在不满者中安插了眼线
What work?
什么工作?
Go to them, as one disaffected with me.
加入他们 假意反叛我
And seek out their thoughts and their strength.
打探他们的想法和实力
Where is Honest John now?
正直的约翰现在在哪?
Have you read this?
你看过这个吗?
He calls upon the nation to rise up against you.
他呼吁全体人民反对你
Do you not sleep easily in your palace at Hampton, my Lord?
在汉普顿的宫廷寝食不安了 大人?
The country was pleased to show its gratitude
全体国民很愿意感激
to my Lord for his many services.
大人为国家的奉献
Parliament gave it. I remember not the country being asked.
议会倒是乐于感谢 我记得没人问过国民吧
Perhaps Master Sexby need not act the part of disaffected.
也许塞斯比先生不用装样子就行
I could not tolerate this, Edward. This is open rebellion.
我无法容忍 爱德华 这是公然叛乱
Then put him on trial.
那就开庭公审他
Where's the jury that will find him guilty?
哪个陪审团会判他有罪?
No. No trial.
不 不能公审
If you move against him without the law,
如果你不通过法律途径对付他
the whole of London will burn.
会激起全伦敦的怒火
Do you smell smoke?
你闻到烟味了吗?
Honest John is even now sailing
正直的约翰正被送往泽西岛
for Jersey where the writ of Habeas Corpus does not run.
人身保护令无效的地方
Give me your answer tomorrow.
明天给我答复
Have it now.
现在就有了
I will not act parts.
我不会去卧底
Have a care, Edward.
小心点 爱德华
We must all bend to the times, all of us.
我们不得不向时代低头 所有人
What will not bend may break.
不肯低头的就只有被断送掉了
Tomorrow.
明天
You must pull your wife out of the Ranters, sir.
您必须让贵夫人远离喧嚣派 先生
She does not wear my reins, sir.
她没被我套住缰绳 先生
A pity for her and for you.
我为你们两人遗憾
She runs to her utter destruction.
她正奔向覆灭
How's the game?
游戏玩得怎样了?
Near won, sir.
接近胜利了 先生
Is she debauched? Have you had her yet?
她放荡吗? 你上过她了吗?
Not yet.
还没有
You are too slow.
你动作太慢了
It must happen today. For all to see.
今天一定要做成 让所有人看到
Troopers come to arrest the fornicators.
骑兵警察会来逮捕通奸者
Cry out, Master Joliffe, and I will open your nose like a fig.
若利夫先生 你敢叫 我就让你满脸开花
Now, tell me...
好 告诉我...
what must be done today?
今天到底要做成什么?
A whore will be unmasked...
一个荡妇将会被揭发
Kill him!
杀了他
Christian...
克里斯廷...
..I know you have a true heart...
我知道你有真诚的心...
..but I...
但我...
You wanted freedom, madam.
你想要自由 夫人
It's found you.
它找到了你
You wanted universal love.
你想要博爱
Well, here it is. The genuine resurrection.
这就是了 真正的复兴
The world turned upside down.
世界陷入一片混乱中
And here, your portion...
你也逃不过...
though you made me wait a weary year for it.
尽管你让我苦等了长长的一年
Arrest her!
逮捕她
He that poisoned you is food for dogs now.
给你下药的人已经横尸街头了
He was in paid service.
他是被雇来的
His task, to debauch you
他的任务是引诱你
and bring further ridicule upon the Ranters.
让喧嚣者派沦为笑柄
Who?
谁?
Joliffe.
若利夫
That should have died in Wightham Woods.
本应死在维特汉姆森林的人
Yet he will die...
但他...
and soon.
活不长了
Leave him, Sexby.
别管他 塞斯比
He is an account that must be settled.
他是非除不可的人
I will settle it.
我会解决的
There is food.
这里有食物
Sexby...        Call for coals.
塞斯比...      叫人送些煤来
I will return tonight.
我今晚会回来
Thank you.
谢谢
Are you unwell?
你不舒服吗?
No.
不是
All is well.
我很好
Nothing is ill. I-I will return.
一点病都没有 我...我会回来的
They have silenced Honest John.
他们禁言了正直的约翰
They have murdered Thomas Rainsborough.
杀害了托马斯·雷恩巴勒
There is none but us now.
现在只剩我们了
Can you love a fool?
你会爱上一个傻瓜吗?
For that I have been.
因为我就是一个傻瓜
My love began on the day you married Harry Fanshawe.
自你嫁给哈里·范肖那天起 我就爱上你了
I did not know I had a heart until that hour.
在那之前 我不知道自己还有心
You filled it with...
你让我心填满了...
..unknown creatures,
不明的感觉
whose names were joy
那就是喜悦
and hope.
还有希望
Both sharper blades than any that had cut me before.
比之前伤过我的任何利刃都锋利得多
I have something of yours.
我有你的随身物品
I've kept it on me every day.
每一天都把它带在身上
Then do not part with it now.
那就不要再和它分开
As I will not with you.
就像我不会再离开你
If you will take me.
如果你接受我的话
You do not say "aye", sir.
你没有答应 先生
I cannot take Rainsborough's widow to me
当雷恩巴勒的凶手仍然逍遥法外
while his murderers still walk the earth.
我不能接受他的遗孀
Even yesterday, scenes of abominable lewdness
就在昨天 淫乱的场面
and fornication were uncovered among the Ranters.
和赤裸裸的通奸 就在喧嚣者中出现
While this House nods asleep and speaks of toleration.
而议院却对此行为麻木不仁 大谈宽容
Sirs, this "toleration" will undo us all!
诸位 这种宽容会害死我们所有人
Let the fornicators be brought before magistrates and be punished.
把私通者带到法官面前 接受惩罚
Their lewd ill manners do not argue an end to religious toleration.
他们的下流勾当 不配得到宗教宽容
Now you have other business today, I am told.
我听说今天你们还有别的事要处理
The motion is that this House declares that no authority
动议如下 下议院宣布 无人有权
shall end this House's sessions...
阻止议院议程
Will you persist, sirs?
你们要顽固不化吗 先生们?
..except its own authority.
除了它本身的权力
You will keep yourselves here in perpetuity?!
你要永远赖在这里?
Those for the motion say "Aye".        Aye
同意动议的人请投赞成      赞成
Stop, enough!
住手 够了
I'll put an end to your prattling.
我来替你的废话做个总结吧
You are no Parliament! Get you gone!
你们不是国会!出去!
Go, call them in!
走 让他们进来
Get you gone.
给我出去
Take your hands from me!
把你的手拿开
And take this bauble with you!
把这些垃圾也拿走
Mount Orgruil Isle of Jersey
泽西 奥格尔山城堡
What is this place?
这个是什么地方
Mont Orgeuil.
奥格尔山城堡
In English - "Mount Pride".
英语里的意思是"傲慢之山"
It is your pride has got you your new home.
是你的傲慢换来了这个新家
Do not hope to leave here.
别想离开这里
This is your tomb, sir.
这是你的坟墓 先生
Bring me pen and ink. When Oliver hears of this...
给我拿纸和笔来 等奥利佛听到...
No pen and ink ever again, Master Lilburne.
不会有纸和笔了 李尔本先生
It is the Lord General himself has sent you here.
是将军亲自下令把你送来这里的
And since you may not write, you have no need of candles.
既然你不用写字 就用不上蜡烛了吧
You have doubts, Edward.
你心存怀疑 爱德华
Will you play a part with the Cavalier party?
你愿意去王党里卧底吗?
Do you have agents among all the parties?
你在各党派都有耳目吗?
That you need not know.
这你不用知道
How long have you had agents amongst the Royalist party?
你在王党里潜伏密探有多久了?
Sir,I have other business...
先生 我还有其他事...
Had you agents among the Royalists
当雷恩巴勒被杀时
at the time of Rainsborough's murder?
你是否有人潜伏在王党内?
Why were those men heard to cry out
为什么有人听到呼叫
that they came from Cromwell?
说人是克伦威尔派来的?
I will tell my Lord that your answer was no.
我会告诉大人 你回绝了他的邀请
He will not be pleased.
他会不高兴的
I will tell him myself.
我自己会告诉他
Then find him at Westminster, for there he stays.
那就去国会找他吧 他会一直在那
Sexby...
塞斯比...
Only madmen oppose us now.
现在只有疯子才与我们作对
I pray you be not mad.
但愿你没有疯
At Westminster. Come.
在国会 走吧
Sexby, stay. Talk with me.
塞斯比 别走 跟我谈谈
We talked the night he was cut in pieces. No more talk.
他被刺杀当晚我们已经谈过了 没什么好说的
Edward! Are you with me again?
爱德华 你又站在我这边了吗?
Sexby!
塞斯比
What is it, Edward?
怎么了 爱德华?
My Lord, we came to ask mercy for John Lilburne
大人 我们来为约翰·李尔本求情
and to pray you, when will he have his trial?
请问您 他何时能接受审讯?
Never, madam.
不可能了 夫人
Then when will he be free?
那么他会被开释吗?
Again, never.
同样不可能
When will his wife and children see him?
他的妻子和儿女何时能见到他?
Once more, madam. Never.
夫人 还是一样 不可能
Come, Edward, all this you know.
爱德华 你懂这些的
Stand out of my way.
别挡着我的路
Did you order the murder of Thomas Rainsborough?
是你下令谋害托马斯·雷恩巴勒的吗?
Sexby, no!
塞斯比 不要
He is unwell, my Lord. His brain is hot, he is sick,
他不舒服 大人 他在发热呢 他病了
he is ever your Lordship's loving servant.
他永远是阁下您忠心的仆人
Hurt not a hair on his head.
别伤他一根毫毛
He was a brother to me.
他与我亲如手足
Take him to the coast and put him out of England tonight.
带他去海岸 驱逐出英国
Sexby, if you return ever, I will have you hanged.
塞斯比 如果你再回来 我会绞死你的
Away.
走吧
Farewell, Madam. Settle all accounts.
再会 夫人 把家当安置好
Sexby!
塞斯比
Pray you, let me go with him. He is all I have left now.
求你让我和他一起去 我只有他一个亲人了
Let him go, madam, from whence he came.
让他去吧 夫人 来自何方回到何处
There is fighting in the Low Countries.
那些低地国家有争战
He will find wages there.
他会在那里挣得佣金
Edward was never happy except he was cutting throats.
爱德华只有在封喉索命之时才会感到快乐
He is not for you.
他不适合你
Why do you dally? Where's my wine?
你磨蹭什么呢? 我的酒在哪儿?
I came with what speed I could, sir.
我已经尽快赶来了 先生
Are you impatient?
您这么心急吗?
Truly this day has been a long while in the coming.
这一天我们等了太久了
Well, the Whore is a man again.
哦 婊子又成男人了
You are an abomination in the eyes of God and of all godly men.
在上帝和虔诚的人眼中你是那么令人憎恶
Why have you persecuted me, sirrah?
你为什么处处于我为难 老小子?
Because you are the age, madam.
因为你同这个时代一样 夫人
Weak, womanish, lustful...
脆弱 阴柔 淫荡...
and not a one of you knows where you should be.
而且不知道你应该属于的位置
Where should we be?
我们应该去哪?
You, madam, should be dead.
你 夫人 该去死掉
I watched you hang.
我看着你上绞架
I saw your pretty ankles kicking at the clouds.
我看着你美丽的脚踝在空中踢腾
Would I had pulled the rope myself.
我应该亲手绞死你
Then I would be a phantom.
那我就是个幽灵
And phantoms cannot harm us.
幽灵不能伤人
But, sir, I am not your crippled imaginings.
但是先生 我不是你脑中残存的幻象
I am flesh and blood.
我是鲜活的血肉之躯
Speak not of Edward Sexby, I beg of you.
别再提爱德华·塞斯比了 我求您
He is gone and that is flat.
他必走无疑
Elizabeth Lilburne will not kneel before you
伊丽莎白·李尔本不会屈膝与您
because her husband forbade her ever ask a favour of the tyrant.
因为她丈夫说 不准她向暴君求情
But I kneel on her behalf.
但我代她屈膝于此
Walk with me.
陪我走走
I never looked for ought of this.
我从未寻求过这些责任
I was just a farmer.
我不过是个农民
God showed me the way to lead men in battle.
上帝指引我率军打仗
I never thought to have the nation's care in my...
我从未想到要关照众生于我...
weak sinner's hands.
无力 罪恶的双手
Will you eat a simple supper with me, Angelica?
愿意和我吃顿晚餐吗 安吉丽卡?
So have you forgiven me?
那么 你原谅我了吗?
For what?
原谅什么?
I took a husband from you.
我夺走了你的一个丈夫
You took two.
你夺走了两个
When you sent Thomas Rainsborough to Pontefract,
你派托马斯·雷恩巴勒去潘蒂法克堡
it was to cut the head off the Levellers, was it not?
是为了铲断平等派的头颅 不是吗?
Aye, it was.
对 是的
Did you strike him down, Oliver?
是你刺杀的他吗 奥利佛?
I would have... faced him in the field.
我宁愿...在战场面对面与他交手
I would have...
我宁愿...
..killed him there, with God's help.
在那里把他杀了 籍上帝之力
He was murdered by the Cavaliers, Angelica,
是王党杀了他 安吉丽卡
as God is my witness.
上帝为我作证
And if he had killed you in the field?
那如果他在战场杀死你呢?
A different England.
英格兰会完全不同
If Thomas sat here now, instead of Oliver,
如果托马斯现在坐在这里 而不是奥利佛
what would be different?
会有什么不同?
With Thomas and freedom.
托马斯就是自由
Oliver and tyranny?
奥利佛则是专政?
Oliver and order,
奥利佛维持秩序
Thomas...
托马斯...
and convulsion.
发动暴乱
Then if convulsion, then famine.
暴乱会带来饥荒
If famine then where is the freedom?
而如果饥荒不断又何来自由?
Where is freedom for Honest John?
正直的约翰的自由何在?
Each new day brings another plot to assassinate me
每一天都有企图刺杀我的阴谋
and bring us closer to anarchy and terror.
将我们推向无序与恐慌
In times like this...
在这样的时代...
some of the freedoms we fought for must be sacrificed.
我们奋斗来的某些自由必须牺牲
There is nothing that now stands
我们与覆灭之间
between us and utter destruction,
没有别的障碍
but me.
除了我
Almighty God chose me,
全能的主选择了我
not Thomas Rainsborough nor any one else. He chose me.
不是托马斯·雷恩巴勒或别的人 他选择了我
And he chooses the path I must now follow.
他选好了我必须走的路
I would have your understanding
希望你能理解
of what I must now give to the nation.
我现在必须为这个国家做什么
Which is what?
做什么?
They will never be settled until they have a King again.
除非重立国王 否则他们无法安定
And what is the word "King" but a bauble,
当然"国王"一词毫无价值
it's a feather in the cap.
它不过是帽上的浮羽
Well, why not in mine?
为什么不由我来呢?
I thought Honest John had lost his senses
我曾以为正直的约翰失去理智
when he told us this day would come.
才会告诉我们这一天会到来
So did I, madam.
我也是 夫人
Well, then...
那好吧...
King Oliver I.
奥利佛一世国王
And England will have another King, chosen by God.
英格兰又要有个国王了 还是上帝选的
Was so much blood spilt for so little?
那么多鲜血抛洒得竟如此不值
I came to petition you for Elizabeth Lilburne.
我为伊丽莎白·李尔本向您请愿
What is your answer, my Lord?
您的答案呢 大人?
Your petitions are granted.
你的请愿获准了
She shall have a pension. She may visit the island.
她可以领粮饷 也可以去岛上探视
Angelica.
安吉丽卡
Prepare Elizabeth.
要伊丽莎白做好准备
Freeborn John Lilburne is...
自由的约翰·李尔本已经...
broken in pieces.
颓败不堪
Fare you well, Oliver.
再会 奥利佛
We shall never meet again.
我们不会再见面了
What? Shall Honest John Lilburne die?
"正直的约翰·李尔本难道该死?"
Six and 60,000 will know the reason why!
"问问那六万六千人" (伦敦传单)
But where are the six and 60,000?
可那六万六千人在哪?
Not here. Nowhere.
不在这 见不到了
Nowhere.
见不到了
Empty words
空洞之词
spoken in another world.
只存在于隔世
John?
约翰?
The Tyrant commanded I should die with no further sight of you.
那暴君下令 我死前不会见到你了
How can you be here?
你怎么在这里?
It matters not how, John.
那无关紧要了 约翰
We are here.
我们来了
Do you bring me pen and ink?
你给我带笔和墨水了吗?
No, John.
没有 约翰
I bring you what is better.
我给你带来的更好
A first sight of your son, Benomy.
见你儿子第一眼 本诺明
How here?
怎么在这?
The Tyrant will free me?
暴君要释放我了?
No, John.
没有 约翰
Angelica!
安吉丽卡
Here is your son, sir.
这是您的儿子 先生
If he frees me not,
如果他没还我自由
then by what means are you come here?
那你们怎么可能来?
He is ill. Take the boy.
他病了 把孩子带走
Come here, boy.
过来 孩子
Behold! Behold your abandoned father!
看看 看看你被遗弃的父亲
Did I not forbid that you should ask the tyrant any favour?
我没禁止过你去向暴君求情吗?
I asked him, John.
是我求的他 约翰
I don't know who you are, madam.
我不认识你 夫人
I don't know this boy child. I have no son.
我不认识这个孩子 我没有儿子
I know only this.
我只知道
The woman I formerly loved.
这个我曾深爱的女人
The woman that you "formerly loved",
这个你"曾深爱"的女人
gave her life without question
毫不犹豫就献出了自己的人生
or complaint to a man "In love with a crown of thorns"!
对她"享受苦行"的男人从无怨言
Think, sir,
想想吧 先生
what I might have been had I not loved a man
如果不是爱着一个日复一日
who each new day nailed himself to the cross of freedom.
把自己钉上自由的十字架的人 我会是怎样?
And where is that freedom now, sir?
如今这自由又在哪呢 先生?
And where was that freedom ever for me?
这又何曾是我的自由?
John, I couldn't bring you pen and paper.
约翰 我不能带纸笔给你
I feared they might execute you if you took up the pen.
我怕你再拿起笔 他们会处决你的
I have feared that all our lives.
我一辈子都在恐惧这个
No matter now, Beth.
无所谓了 伊丽莎白
It was all mistaken.
全都错了
What was mistaken, John?
什么错了 约翰?
To change the temporal world.
我们想改造俗世
All that matters is what waits for us.
其实身后的世界才是最重要的
Elizabeth, he knows not what he says.
伊丽莎白 他在说胡话
Indeed I do, madam.
我很清醒 夫人
When I am free, I will take up my cross.
等我自由了 我要拿起十字架
I will crucify the pride in me.
我会钉死我的骄傲
I will tell Oliver do the same.
我会劝奥利佛也这么做
I cannot tell him.
我对他说不出口
Cannot tell me?
说不出口
Cannot tell me what, madam?
说不出口什么 夫人?
Though he will call himself Lord Protector still,
尽管他会继续自称"护国公"
Oliver is to be King.
奥利佛要登基当国王了
Forgive me.
原谅我
For what?
原谅什么?
All.
一切
Until the last of my days,
只要我一息尚存
my proudest boast will ever be
我最大的骄傲永远是
that I was the wife of Freeborn John Lilburne.
我是自由人约翰·李尔本的妻子
Bring him!
抬过来
Hurry, sirs.
快点 先生们
Put him in.
放下去
Here lies Freeborn...
这里安息着自由人...
No speeches.
不许致悼词
I will be damned before I will let you silence her!
我宁死也不允许你封她的口
This is my land you're standing on.
你脚下是我的土地
Madam, I was told no speeches.
夫人 上级有令不许致悼词
To your work, sirs.
把活干完吧 先生们
And you to your homes.
你们回家去吧
I thought I had lost you.
我以为我失去你了
Not yet.
还没有呢
Good sir.
好心的先生
When the world began its turning,
当世界开始颠倒
I little thought I would be turned so utterly.
我未曾料到我也会如此脱胎换骨
Nor I.
我也没有
Come.
来吧
Mistress mine.
我的爱人
First peep.
清晨第一眼
The dark is clearing...
天刚泛白
like mist uprising from the water land where I began.
就像我最初看到的雾气升腾的水面
Jack has his Jill.
"哥儿爱姐儿"
Then naught shall go ill.
"两两无参差" (仲夏夜之梦)
Sexby, why have you come back?
塞斯比 你回来干什么来了?
To kill the King.
刺杀国王
Every schoolboy will learn the name of Edward Sexby.
每个小学生都将学到爱德华·塞斯比的名字
That he set England free of its chains.
他为英格兰解脱了枷锁
And I will be free.
我也会自由
What is it you look for?
你要寻找什么呢?
Nothing, madam.
什么也不要 夫人
But I swear on my life that I do love thee.
可我以生命发誓 我真的爱你
Then give this up...
那就罢手吧
..and come with me to the New World.
和我一起去新大陆
You must have the life you choose.
你一定要过你心所向的生活
I fear my ending will not be yours.
恐怕你我终将分道扬镳了
Must all end in blood?
一切都得以鲜血了结吗?
Aye...
对
..all must end in blood.
一切都得以鲜血了结
One week hence,
一周之后
on the day of Oliver's glory, wait for me at the sea.
奥利佛登基之日 在海边等我
If the parish bells welcome England's new King,
如果教堂钟声敲响 欢迎英格兰新的国王
think not to see me again.
就不用指望再见我了
I will not be given to the butchers.
我不会苟且偷生的
That day will shake the world, madam.
那一天将会震撼世界 夫人
And all the blood will not have been in vain.
一切流血牺牲都将有个交待
Do you know me, Angelica?
你懂我吗 安吉丽卡?
Aye, Edward.
懂 爱德华
You are yourself.
你就是你自己
There are many now among us
如今我们很多人
who see him as a traitor and a tyrant.
都称他为叛徒和暴君
He will get the nation's thanks, if he does this.
无论谁得手 整个国家都会感谢他
This is your place, sir.
就是这里了 先生
Here I will make my horse seem lame.
走到这里我会绊住我的马腿
His carriage will have to stop.
他的马车就得停下来
Good morrow to you.
各位早安
Good morrow, Your Highness.
早安 陛下
Nay.
不
Let me be Old Noll a few hours more.
让我再做一阵老奥利佛吧
Toop?
图普
Today you ride before me.
今天你为我开道
I recall a time I rode before you, do you remember?
我也为你开过一回道 记得吗?
At Kineton fight, My Lord.
在金内顿战役 大人
It was a brave fight.
英勇的一战
Aye, My Lord.
对 大人
I remember.
我记得
I remember you well.
我清楚记得你
Did you not fight near me
你不是随我救下了
when we saved Honest John and his dragoon?
正直的约翰和他的骑兵吗?
Very near, My Lord.
确实是随着您 大人
Do you remember Free Born John? How he fought...
你还记得战场上的自由人约翰吗?
until he was one heartbeat away from paradise.
殊死搏斗 决不罢休
I robbed him of a martyr's death
我夺走了他壮烈牺牲的机会
and he never forgave me.
他一直没有原谅我
I remember John Lilburne every night in my prayers, My Lord.
我每夜都记得约翰·李尔本祈祷 大人
As do I, Toop.
我也是 图普
Did you ever think this day would come?
你料到过会有这一天吗?
No...
没有
My Lord, I did not.
大人 我没料到
Cromwell comes!
克伦威尔驾到
Clear a way for the lord protector!
为护国公让路
May God forgive me.
愿上帝宽恕我
My Lord, I cannot let you proceed any further.
大人 我不能带您朝前走了
God save the Lord Protector!
上帝保佑护国公
Long live his Highness! God save the Lord Protector!
陛下万岁 上帝保佑护国公
'On the day Sexby died,
塞斯比死的那天
'the new life he left me was already quick within me.'
他留在我体内的新生命已经临近了
'After Beth entered her new world.
伊丽莎白降临她的新世界之后
'Oliver departed the old one he'd turned upside down.'
奥利佛也告别了他颠覆的旧世界
Oh, Lord...
主啊
Give them consistency of judgment.
保佑他们的判断始终如一吧
Our father...
同奉天父
One heart.
同心同德
And mutual love.
彼此相爱
'The second King Charles came over the water,
查理二世国王渡海而来
'and the fountains of London ran with wine.'
整个伦敦都心花怒放
Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
Look up there in those branches.
抬头看看那些树枝
Do you see anything?
你看见什么了吗?
I see leaves and sky.
我看见叶子和天空
'All my men were dead.'
与我一道的人都死了
'Their hopes and dreams gone with them,'
他们的希望和梦想也随之而去
'yet we are the world we live in,
然而我们自己组成了我们生活的世界
'the world we love in.
我们所爱的世界
'These were the life and times of Angelica Fanshawe.
这便是安吉丽卡·范肖的生平和时代
'In the final account, there is love
归根结底 我们有爱
and those sharp blades...
还有无坚不摧的刀剑...
'joy and hope.'
欢乐与希望